What do you do when you have a problem?
当你遇到问题时会怎么做？
Do you go to an expert, ask your friends to come up with an idea?
是向专家求助，还是让朋友出主意？
Or, given the chance, would you ask a crowd of strangers for a solution?
或者，如果有机会，你会向一群陌生人寻求解决方案吗？
It may sound strange, but it has spurred more than a few successful innovations.
这听起来可能很奇怪，但它已经催生了不少成功的创新。
That’s the thinking behind a 'challenge prize'.
这就是“挑战奖”背后的理念。
Challenge prizes come in many shapes and sizes but the basic concept remains the same.
挑战奖有多种形式和规模，但基本概念不变。
Rather than consulting and paying an expert to innovate a solution, you offer the prize up to anyone who believes they can solve it and present the first to do so with a prize.
你不必咨询或付费让专家来创新解决方案，而是向任何自认为能解决问题的人提供奖励，并向首位成功解决问题的人颁奖。
This might sound odd - many would argue, 'Who is better qualified than an expert?' But actually, not using one seems to result in a great deal of thinking outside of the box.
这听起来可能很奇怪——许多人会说，“谁比专家更有资格呢？”但实际上，不依赖专家似乎能催生大量的创新性思维（thinking outside of the box）。
Some argue that formal education can kill creativity because it sometimes only teaches a single solution to a problem or single method to achieve a task.
有人认为，正规教育可能会扼杀创造力，因为它有时只教授解决问题的单一方案或完成任务的单一方法。
In the same way, some suggest that experts can suffer from tunnel vision.
同样，有人认为专家可能会思维受限。
"If we launch an XPRIZE and it's just the 'experts' that come out and compete, they're usually the ones that will tell us it can't be done." says Marcus Shingles, former CEO of the XPRIZE Foundation, which organises challenge prizes today.
“如果我们发起一项XPRIZE，而只有‘专家’出来竞争，他们通常会告诉我们这不可能完成。”现任XPRIZE基金会（该基金会如今组织挑战奖）前首席执行官马库斯・辛格尔顿（Marcus Shingles）说。
There are other advantages too.
还有其他优势。
"You're not asking people to use a particular solution set on how to solve that problem.
“你没有要求人们使用解决问题的特定方案，因此会获得巨量的多样性（diversity）。”
So you get this tremendous amount of diversity." adds Shingles.
辛格尔顿补充道。
And because the crowd acts like an impromptu think tank, its lateral thinking can throw up issues that may have been overlooked.
而且，由于人群就像一个临时智囊团，其横向思维（lateral thinking）可能会提出一些被忽视的问题。
Challenge prizes were most popular during the 18th and 19th centuries, but have received renewed interest more recently.
挑战奖在18和19世纪最为流行，但最近再次引起了人们的兴趣。
Historically, many practical inventions have been conceived in this way – for example, the tin can.
从历史上看，许多实用的发明都是通过这种方式构思出来的——例如锡罐。
More recently, Virgin Galactic, a company hoping to commercialise space flight, developed out of the Ansari XPRIZE 2004 winner Tier One.
最近，希望将太空飞行商业化的维珍银河（Virgin Galactic）公司就源自2004年安萨里XPRIZE的获奖者“一级”（Tier One）。
They successfully launched a reusable spacecraft that left the Earth's atmosphere twice in two weeks.
他们成功发射了一艘可重复使用的航天器，该航天器在两周内两次离开地球大气层。
The prize was $10m.
奖金为1000万美元。
However, there are dangers connected to blue-sky thinking.
然而，天马行空的思考（blue-sky thinking）也存在风险。
"You don't want to be creating a challenge prize which incentivises people to solve a problem where there is no demand," says Tris Dyson, executive director of challenge prizes at Nesta, a UK-based innovation foundation.
“你不希望设立一个挑战奖，激励人们去解决一个没有需求的问题，”英国创新基金会Nesta的挑战奖执行董事特里斯・戴森（Tris Dyson）说。
This happened in 1979 where a Kremer prize of £100,000 was claimed by the first person to fly under human power across the English Channel.
1979年就发生过这样的事：克雷默（Kremer）设立的10万英镑奖金被首位以人力飞行穿越英吉利海峡的人获得。
Despite its successful completion, it has not led to the adoption of human-powered flight as a form of travel.
尽管成功完成了飞行，但人力飞行并未成为一种旅行方式。
And of course, there are those who invest their personal time and money only to see no return at all: someone else claims the prize, or they find that the reward does not match the resources they invested.
当然，还有一些人投入了个人时间和金钱，却根本看不到回报：要么被别人拿走了奖金，要么发现回报与投入的资源不匹配。
The pros and cons of challenge prizes affect both problem-setters and problem-solvers.
挑战奖的利弊既影响问题设定者，也影响问题解决者。
But they don’t seem to be going out of style anytime soon.
但它们似乎短期内不会过时。
To many, the challenge to innovate, the lure of the prize and the prestige of being first is too much to resist.
对许多人来说，创新的挑战、奖金的诱惑和拔得头筹的声望让人难以抗拒。
And there’s no solution for that.
而这一点，尚无解决之道。